before we begin we would like to welcome
all the students who came for the yoga
teacher training course that starts
tomorrow and uh if you didn't register
today three please come tomorrow at 11:
to the dining area for
registration and then after that you're
going to have an orientation to the
course at 1:45 on the garden platform
and at 4:30 uh we'll start the course
here there will be an inauguration
ceremony here in the temple so we
welcome uh all the students for this
course and tonight we continue with the
program with GHA M roach on what is
Nirvana and how do we get there let us
[Applause]
welcome
that's
[Music]
for
hi right uh we're going to play two
we've been playing I don't know all
kinds of strange things but tonight
uh well we heard you were tired of the
same old Cur things uh uh so we're going
to play some Tibetan two Tibetan pieces
okay uh one is uh the Mantra of Tara the
lady of
Liberation MTI and then uh the other is
a very unusual Mantra usually mantras in
Tibet all mantras in Tibet are Sanskrit
except one and that's the uh Mantra of
jetona who is the founder of our Lage
and the teacher of the first diala so
there's a beautiful Mantra uh to him
which is in the Tibetan language the
only one we're going to do those
to
[Music]
oh
to
so to
today
[Music]
so
to to
[Music]
so
to
[Music]
to so
oh
to to to
[Music]
to
[Applause]
[Music]
my
so come
[Music]
[Applause]
CH Lo
s droping
shall
[Music]
BL
we
way
T
dream
can one
more
[Music]
[Applause]
come
oh my Lord
oh
oh my
Lord
oh
[Music]
my
oh
[Music]
oh my
Lord my
Lord
oh
my
for
St
so uh we've been talking about Nana
those of you who haven't been here and
um exploring what it is and how we get
[Music]
there and and we've been saying that
Nirvana
was uh the ability to stop your negative
emotions
forever like you would just I mean it's
a little difficult to imagine
uh never getting upset again ever or
never being unhappy again or depressed
or never being jealous of
anyone um never wanting the third
donut you know at all I mean it's a
little bit difficult to imagine so I've
heard some people say it would be boring
that life is only appreciated by by the
suffering to compare it to but I I think
that's almost said a bad word
uh uh and they say there's a school of
thought that you couldn't recognize
happiness without sadness and that's not
true it's just not true okay uh it would
be nice to be happy and it would be nice
not to ever get angry again okay um and
there is such a thing and that's Nirvana
so Nirvana is not
disappearing uh into some personal
blissful
state where you ignore everybody in the
world okay it's not that Nirvana
is very famous in in
Buddhism it's the permanent ending of
your negative emotions because you have
seen Ultimate Reality directly that's
part of the definition so all of us here
in the last couple nights having a great
desire to reach n
ourselves I mean the part about not
whenever getting upset again sounds good
uh so exactly how do you carry that out
in Practical terms with a daily
meditation uh with regard to this
ultimate truth thing like what this
ultimate truth really mean what is
ultimate truth okay and we were talking
about uh it's a difficult idea ultimate
truth is the absence of something okay
ultimate truth is the absence of
something so like you go to Atlanta you
sneak
up uh to Atlantis weid it the other day
but not very well um and uh you take
your credit card you know and you don't
take a lot of stuff cuz then everybody
knows you're going to at lce so uh you
just put a credit card in your pocket
and you go over there you know any place
you eat there it's going to cost you you
know 30 bucks just to set foot in there
and then uh
and then you you know you eat something
you have a nice dinner and then they
bring you the bill and then
you you reach for your pocket you know
and you're like oh my God you know I
bent over on the beach I remember about
halfway down you know
and and it's gone and it's that Nana is
that kind of a feeling and ultimate
reality is that kind of a feeling
something you thought was there
something you always thought was
there is
gone all right and that's how we Define
Ultimate Reality okay so Ultimate
Reality is the absence of of something
that's what helps it be Eternal and
unchanging because uh this is I'm going
to go to a little meat tonight okay
uh the only unchanging things in the
world actually in our system are
absences of things is there we gave an
example last night is there a
two-headed 34t purple elephant rampaging
through this Temple right now you can
say no okay you can say no so we can say
there's an absence of that kind of
elephant in this room okay and it could
never be more or less you see you
couldn't say it was 95% absent you know
and then I had students who you know
rais their hand and said what if the
elephant comes to the door and his trunk
is hanging in the tempo then it's like
he's only 95% out okay I mean that would
be okay
almost uh except those kind elant don't
exist anyway you see what I mean you
can't say that uh it could never
be that there was 95% of a purple
elephant not here or 25% you see it is
it it will always
be 100% absolute okay therefore it never
changes it doesn't vary it doesn't get
more and less absent all right what
helps make Ultimate Reality ultimate is
that it never varies it's it's really is
Ultimate and there's nothing to compare
it to it's beyond uh it's a higher
reality okay and there's and in that
place it's 100% Ultimate Reality okay
and it's never less than that cannot be
because it's the absence of something
now get this okay ready you have to get
this I didn't do too much last night
because I didn't want to give you
indigestion uh Ultimate Reality is the
absence of a thing which was never there
in the first place which could not have
been there just like a two-headed purple
elephant all right so Ultimate Reality
so I'm going to ask you question is is
nirvana Ultimate
Reality he said no is it not an
absence is didn't we say Nirvana was the
absence of
something didn't we Define n as the
ending or absence of something didn't we
what what's it the absence of your CLS
your negative emotions did those ever
exist yes
I'm proof of it I
mean I mean my jealousy is classical
classic okay it's there okay Nirvana is
the absence of something which certainly
did exist up until the time you achieved
Nirvana and then you got rid of it so by
this definition could it be Ultimate
Reality no because Ultimate Reality we
said is the absence of
something which was never there okay
then you know that's our philosophy
let's take it down to real life
[Music]
okay and we were saying someone came up
to you and called you stupid which never
happens right like someone called out
can came up to you and and criticized
you in some way or another you know
Swami G says we meditate on Pizza during
our our meditation time but that's not
true uh we meditate on the people who
criticize
us I think the pizza is between that
uh so mainly I mean most of us we
meditate on on people who hurt us I mean
that's a big subject for meditation
people who have heard this in our life
right let's say someone who called you
stupid recently right and we were
describing that person we
said uh they were coming we said it
was it was to prove you're stupid if you
do what if you call him stupid back it
proves they're
right okay
why
why yeah because by calling back you
plant a newonics in your mind to see
them call you stupid again next week all
right and that's sarm that's the meaning
of sarm something bad happens to you you
respond negatively and thereby plant a
new seed to have this the same stupid
thing happen to you all right that
sense the iron
of all of this the tragedy of all of
this we were saying is that the person
you're calling stupid is coming
from you okay they're not calling you
stupid biotic it's not some random thing
okay they they come from a karmic seat
in your mind which who put there there's
a thing about karmic seats no one can
put a caric seat in anybody's mind
except themselves that's just the rule
of the universe okay nobody can put a
seed in your mind except yourself if you
want to have someone call you stupid it
is required by the universe that you
call somebody else stupid first so where
did the first stupid
start really which came first chicken or
the
egg what would what would Hinduism say
and what would Buddhism say same they
would say the same
thing logically which came first the
person calling you stupid or you calling
somebody else
there's no it's a trick question there
is no it's been
forever it's been forever okay there
cannot be a person to call you stupid
unless you have called someone else
stupid okay it's not
possible and you can't call someone else
stupid until they tell you you're
stupid okay that it both of our systems
say there was no there's no there cannot
be a beginning um okay we've been stupid
Forever uh now now big question
okay when you get angry at a person who
calls you stupid right can you get angry
at a person who calls you stupid and at
the same time entertain the knowledge
that they are coming from
you is it possible to blame them at the
same time as you know you your fault I
mean you can blame them 10 seconds later
or 20 seconds later but is it possible
for one mind to hold the two thoughts
this person is my fault and they're
yelling at me is their fault is it
possible for one human mind to hold both
of those at the same time we say no we
say not possible we they say there's two
Cowboys in town the bad guy there's
Dirty Harry and there's I don't know the
other guy the me mean the the mean the
Bad and the Ugly whatever okay and then
what does the one always say to the
otherin room Ain room in this town for
both of us you know your mind is like
that you cannot
simultaneously understand that the
person is coming from you and blame them
for calling you to do good it's not
possible it's just not possible
okay why you can't think two opposite
things at the same time technically you
can think them about a millisecond apart
but you can't think it at the syn back
not possible okay in the next second you
can say they you know you can blame them
but ignorance VI and a cannot exist in
the same mind at the same millisecond
it's not possible okay the Mind cannot
hold
both
um so I have a question for you and you
got to stay with me okay don't space
out
um you can do that tomorrow during
meditation
um so if a person yells at you and you
get angry at them and you feel that it's
their
fault does that person
exist that's the person
who's yeah does a person calling you
stupid who comes from themselves exist
or not no such thing there's no such
thing there never was and there couldn't
be because all things come from Karma
all things come from seas in your mind
okay there is no person who ever
criticized you who was coming from their
side there was never such a person
that's the meaning of Maya illusion okay
there has never been such a
person the the tragedy of life is all
the people you get angry at don't
exist okay the people you have ever
gotten a upset in your life if you could
get upset at them didn't
exist okay that's the tragedy okay now
now understand this and then we can move
on all right understand one more thing
the
absence of a person calling you stupid
who's not coming from you is the meaning
of Ultimate Reality and that's all and
that's it okay no more big mystery about
it okay I'll say it again
uh the
absence of a person who's calling you
stupid who's not coming from you is is
what ultimate reality is and that's all
and it and in in this girlo that's it
okay that's Ultimate Reality all right
got it if you saw that would it help
you if you saw that would it help you
it's the only thing that can really help
you okay we say and we went through the
other viewpoints yesterday we went
through five other ultimate realities
yesterday they they're helpful but they
don't stop your your cles for they
cannot okay and then back to Sham
Christ's
question
uh try to grasp this the reason that the
higher schools say you cannot drop out
of Nirvana is because once you let's say
you're like walking by a store you know
you're driving by one of the stores uh
in Nassau on the way from the airport to
here right and you know how you're
talking to somebody and you you halfway
see something out of the corner of your
eye you know and you're thinking oh that
that lady has a nice dress on and you
turn your head and you see that she's a
a mannequin you see that she's a just a
plastic uh
mannequin in the store can you can you
then for the rest of the drive desire to
ask her out for a
day no is it
possible is it possible that will come
into your M to ask for dat I don't
unless you're
really unless you went to the bar and
the just before that you see it's not
possible to have that kind of wanting
for her or to you know to ask her for
her phone number or her email address
you know because you saw that she wasn't
at all uh a person okay and and the
reason you can't drop out of Nirvana
once you reach nirvana is that it is
based on seeing that the people you
thought were there were never there and
you can't how can you forget that you
know how can you just suddenly decide
the mannequin how can you drive back to
the store
and ask her for email you see I mean you
have to have some huge laps of of
understanding okay it's un for real this
is for Real once you've
seen directly that's a different thing
okay but once you've seen
thatly that the things and people around
you are coming from you you can't go
back you'll never go back you can't go
back okay it's not it doesn't happen
it's not possible you won't drive back
right and that's why Nirvana stays
that's why you stay in Nana all right so
now I wanted to go on to a different
subject
um we've been exploring Nirvana as the
end of uh your negative emotions and by
the way they're also the end for the
Deep seeds for them the deepest vasas or
S scars for those cles are also
destroyed by video but that's another
understanding some people add that to
the definition um
but there's this thing uh how do you say
you know the Wheel of Life okay if you
have a reading okay I put a wheel of
life in there for you all right there's
a picture what page is
it
26 26
26 look at page 26 of your reading okay
uh that's a picture and we taught it
last time we were here a year ago uh
it's called C or uh B chakra sansar
chakra uh it's a painting which was
designed by the Buddha himself to
illustrate how you stay in sansara okay
and then a lot of people correctly
Define nirvana as the end of SAR okay
getting out of sansar all right
so you can they call this the wheel of
sansara and we have to explore what
sansara is because you can Define uh
Nirvana as Moka or MTI uh from sansar
okay so what is sansar all right and
here you have a picture of it all right
this is a picture made by you know the
best for us the best Authority Lord
Buddha himself designed this painting
and it's been copied ever since and the
instructions for it are in the
vas uh which isn't a Sutra but that's
another
story it's a sh it's made by a human
anyway in the middle not the middle
middle but you can see five can you see
five different
Realms uh like about halfway in there
are five different Realms if you look at
12:00 and you go to the left you can see
like two groups of people they happen to
be fighting with each other these are
the SAS and the auras these are the gods
and the Demar Gods okay uh the forces
that people in you know that we we've
been talking about okay so there's a
traditional uh conflict permanent
conflict going on between uh Subic
forces and Majestic forces the evil
forces okay these are this this is even
represented in the in the you can see
there's a division and they are fighting
with each other okay next down on the
left is the realm of animals
M and next down 6:00 at the bottom is
the nas the hell reals okay eight cold
Hells eight hot HS and a bunch
of extra Hells okay and uh then up from
that on the r 3:00 are the Realms of
pretas pretas are like people who
couldn't stop beating Pringles in this
life and when they die they have this un
insensible desire they are Spirit beings
uh that are difficult to see but their
Essence is that they they were so
obsessed with food or or things like
that in this life that they are born
constantly searching for food in a
spirit in a spirit being okay PR and
then the next one up around 1:00 those
are the Realms of humans okay those are
the Realms of the humans so we say um
what do they call
it punch this is The Wheel of Life this
is the wheel of sansara this is the
wheel of five Realms of suffering okay
it doesn't matter where you're born how
many of these Realms can we
see only two okay a normal human being
can only see two of these Realms human
and animal okay the rest EX L you can
perceive them in meditation if you learn
to meditate well uh you can perceive
them uh but I don't think it's so it's
not important for me to convince you
there are five Realms uh if you die you
can be born in one of those Realms and
that rebirth is is sometimes called
sansar okay because this is the wheel of
SAR so reasonably people have said that
Nirvana was not coming back ever again
right and and we we say there are four
steps in a person's spiritual
career uh there are there are four
stages that you can Define I think Swami
G today would have called
it what do you call
thata okay uh a high state of
realization but not all the way uh we
would say
these four levels start from there so a
person who's really enjoying the fruits
of their spiritual practice can be
divided into four the lowest of them is
someone who just saw Ultimate Reality
directly can you see Ultimate Reality
directly right
now we say you cannot it's not possible
to see it unless you are in very very
deep meditation extremely deep
meditation okay and there's training on
how to get there but something that's
very very useful to have that threshold
experience is uh what I want you to
meditate on tomorrow okay so what I want
you to try tomorrow we we've been doing
these meditations every night okay I
give you a meditation each night you
forget it and you no I mean you you do
it the next morning I hope okay so we
started out the first meditation was you
were supposed to
figure out what's your number one clure
you know and I told you mine is jealousy
and I have honed it to a science you
know like my mind is filled with it all
day about the smallest stupidest things
I can have jealousy about anything you
know CU I meditated on it so so well
okay so you know the first night you
were supposed to to decide what's your
number some people said anger some
people said low self-esteem some people
said potato chip desire you know that's
okay then the second night uh what was
it you were supposed to catch it coming
up in your mind or at least review the
last few days and see how many times did
it come up in your mind then we said try
to get in touch with how it felt when
you got it and it feels terrible okay by
the way and that's the definition of
aesia of a negative emotion in Buddhism
is a
a thought which disturbs the Peace of
Mind of the person who has the thought
okay that's the definition of a so we
were supposed to in our third meditation
we were supposed
to just bring up one of your favorite
CLA and see how bad it makes you feel
right and just be aware of how it ruins
your day right how your your CLA are
pretty much the reason for your
unhappiness throughout the day when one
comes up you feel unhappy it ruins
it can ruin 15 minutes of your day it
can ruin an hour it can ruin the whole
day you get angry at one person somebody
calls you stupid in the afternoon in the
kitchen and then you say something back
and then you think about it all day and
it ruins your peace of mind as long as
it's ruining your peace of mind that's a
claure okay so then we said watch your
claas okay just observe how bad they
feel then we said try to observe how
good it feels when you do the opposite
right so the other day I was praising
somebody and I was thinking why don't
you just do that guess you Michael
instead of being jealous of people
because it's so joyful to tell someone
how cool they are right rather than
being jealous of them you know so then
we were talking about how nice now
tomorrow would I'd like you to try is
something else okay get this okay I want
you
to
review and this will help you see
emptiness directly this will help you
see Ultimate Reality directly this is an
exercise which could which could throw
you into the direct perception of
mity try to get in
touch with how the person you don't
like doesn't exist and never did just
try to get in touch with them okay like
the person you're jealous of or the
person who called you
stupid whose fault is not yours okay I'm
adding that ready got that I'm adding
that for who you are not to blame
who you didn't create all right try to
get in
touch with the person who's calling you
stupid or that you don't like who you
didn't create
yourself okay got it where will they
be they don't exist okay but I want you
to get in touch with that I want you to
feel it because that can trigger the
direct perception of Ultimate Reality
because that is Ultimate Reality the
fact that the people you don't like
don't exist and never could have it's
ultimate real do they exist yes do they
call you stupid yes do they come from
themselves no so we're very you have to
be very uh clever you have to be very V
you have to have good
discrimination do the people calling you
stupid exist yes is that a bad thing
yes is it their fault
no is the person whose fault it is out
there no okay just try to get in touch
with that for tomorrow's meditation okay
think of someone you don't like think of
something they did to hurt you and then
try to imagine them as someone who's not
your
fault and that don't exist and it never
did and if you get good at that you can
go into the direct perception of
ultimate real okay
what happens then so in in the Buddhist
system via that would be roughly via
your first direct perception of Ultimate
Reality okay we say that's the beginning
of the way out that's called gun Chupa
gupa means stream enterer someone who
has entered the stream I like to call it
someone who has popped down on the
conveyor belt okay it means there's a
conveyor Bel going to
Nirvana and if you can have that Peak
experience if you can see Ultimate
Reality directly because you practiced
it a lot on the people who irritated
you okay you see if you PR they can be
extremely useful okay all the people
irritate you meditate on the fact that
they're not coming they're not not
coming from you and that's Ultimate
Reality and if you do that enough somay
in a deep meditation you will see
Ultimate Reality directly at that moment
you be become a conveyor
bter they call stream enter okay it
means you are in with minda minda means
there's no way you can't not get there's
no way you can't get to Nirvana after
that you are very quickly going to get
to Nana okay stream Mentor means if you
see Ultimate Reality directly
once you're on the you're on the way and
nothing can stop you okay that's called
stream next one there are four right
next one is called uh Len CH say
Len CH Len means one more time CH means
back come CH means come back once they
call once returner comes back one time
where you can say to this world okay you
can say to this uh this wheel okay it's
the Comm doct it's the desire room okay
there's tiny part of this wheel which is
not the desire but we won't worry about
it okay ch ch means they will have to
take one more rebirth in this wheel okay
in the this in the lower part of in the
bad part of this wheel not as a
de next next one up above that is called
sayic sorry
[Music]
say say
say
say che
che doesn't come back someone who will
not come back to the lower parts of this
wheel there's a tiny part of this wheel
which is kind of cool and you get to
live there a long time as is or
brma okay and and that's not desire real
but that sh means you don't have to come
back to the bad parts of this wheel you
still have to come back to the wheel and
you will suffer in the wheel but at
least you're like in the top 1%
that's called cheron doesn't have to
come back to the lower 99% okay to the
desire part
CH after
that if you if you if you go higher in
your spiritual practice you reach a
thing called Arad say Arad Arad Arad
means enemy Destroyer the Tibetans
translated it as D which means enemy
distor that means they saw the word arat
as being
ariot AR means
enemy it's not just an isra name and H
means uh to strike Hut or H H came into
English
as gun the AG changed
okay
unstruck is the same roote no violence
so means to slay the enemy to kill the
enemy who's the
enemy who's the enemy no Arad means is
the name given to someone who has
reached nirvana that's the name who we
we don't call Nirvana R because it's too
hard to
say right we call them enemy Destroyer
fo Destroyer they have killed the enemy
okay what's the
enemy your own negative emotions
okay and again that can that could
happen tonight and you wouldn't look
different tomorrow but you would have
reached nirvana okay get used to that
you can reach nirvana on Tuesday and
still get assigned to kitchen duty on
Wednesday okay or accting which is worse
cuz it's
permanent so
uh okay all right uh get used toight
right so s by enemy Destroyer me are H
and in this four steps it's defined as a
person who no longer has to come back to
any part of this wheel they are beyond
the wheel they they will'll never have
to take another rebirth okay and that's
what you uh think of when somebody says
escapes Sam SAR one of the things you
always hear is oh they don't have to be
reborn anymore and then you know people
I've talked to like Buddhist here me and
J were talking about it yesterday and
day before she said God when I heard
that I was so scared you know I said
where am I going to come back if I don't
get to be a human or a bug or I don't
even get to go into the hell realms I
mean well then what am I going to be you
know is it so desirable not to take
Reaper you know I don't know I grew up
as a Christian it was a big deal that
that you were reborn it was supposed to
be a good thing you know uh or or you
know come back again was supposed to be
a good thing you know so so if someone's
trying to sell you the idea of Nirvana
and they say look it's cool you say why
and you say you know you get to not come
back and then you're like but I want to
see my mom and you have
a you know I'll never hear the fourth
chapter of the G you
know so by the way for
201 so uh know I mean there's this thing
you see enemy Destroyer is the word
given for someone who has reached Nana
and an enemy Destroyer is someone who
doesn't have to come back and to the
wheel anymore anymore okay so now you've
got in my mind I used to have a big
problem here I used to just get to have
a big problem and I got like 14 minutes
to explain why it's
cool some people were saying Nirvana
means you don't have to come back
anymore and then some people were saying
no Nirvana is the end of your negative
emotions and there are very uh
elaborate uh bodies of scripture to to
describe each one you see and then it
was just confusing for me all the time
you know some people are saying Nirvana
when you get to Nirvana you don't have
to come back anymore and and you've
escaped
sansar and then you escape this reel and
the five forms of rebirth okay I mean
they weren't too clear on what I was
going to be after that okay and then the
other people were saying no
no you see Ultimate Reality you stop
your negative emotions you could be
sitting here tomorrow and be in Nirvana
but then these other guys say I have to
leave The Wheel of Life if I get to
Nirvana got the problem you see the
problem half the people are saying you
get to Nirvana when you get out of
sansara and sansara is the five Realms
of reer and then half the people are
saying you get to Nirvana when you stop
your negative emotions
okay so to really appreciate the the
answer to the problem it's a beautiful
answer and it's a beautiful idea okay
you have to try to understand what
rebirth is all right you have to
understand what we both
means I'll do the pen
thing okay I'm I got to do this fast so
you got to hang in there I know it's
late they put me at the end which is
really cruel okay uh what is this
pig it's a pen if a dog came in here
well they
see they would a small dog would bite it
right they were Che who's
right you can say both reasonbly okay
dogs leave the room and turkeys
and we were having this huge debate
about whether we were turkeys anymore or
not I told yingbo he was a turkey either
way anyway um if I throw the pen here
all the dogs leave the room all the
humans leave the room
then which one is it NE you can say
neither and that's sh in in Buddhism
that's emptiness it's not some black
hole okay you just got like 20 years of
teaching no I mean that's EMP is nothing
more nothing less okay if I look at this
object and see a pen why why do I see a
pen because there's a kic seed in my
mind who put it there me how did I put
it
there
I gave a pen to someone who needed a pen
okay I I showed the kindness to another
person I gave a pen to someone who
needed a pen I watched my hand go out it
recorded everything there was an image
of a pen put into my subconscious that's
a kic state and then you know later I
pick up this subject and I see a pen
okay question for you is the pen coming
this way or is the pen coming this way
you can show me with your
hand is the pen coming this way or is
the pen coming this
way it's got to be coming this way why
AR why the dog doesn't Z okay it's very
simple if it was coming this way a dog
would see a pen okay it's got to be
coming this way okay it has to be uh I
have a seed in my mind how why I put it
there how did I put it there I offered
it to another person I offered a pen to
another person that's how you put a seed
in your mind caric seat right so I have
that seed it opens I see it as a pen
it's so fast that you're not aware of it
it's so fast this whole process you know
kic seep Bas opens uh projected out onto
this object and you think it's a pen and
and you feel that it's coming from its
own side you really do okay but now you
know it's not right because up the door
door it's so simple it's so simple it's
not a pen from its own side and it's not
a CH
from by itself without dogs and and
people it's not it's neither got
it what's
this it's an
arm is it coming this way or this way
yeah yeah you're all right those of you
who are awake which is about
four you no they went like this they
said they aren't because all things are
are the same okay understand the pen and
you understand everything all right all
things where did we say the guy who
calls you stupid is coming
from we dropped a few
people okay he's also coming like
okay get used to it everything we call a
a synonym in Buddhism for a person who
hasn't reached the V is means someone
who thinks things are coming this way
okay so they they are coming this way
okay things are coming this
way if I had not reached out to help
other people with my hands in arms okay
get this if I had not in my past reached
out to help people who needed help with
these limbs I would be seeing a
paw no try to gos that it's true if I
had not helped people with these
limbs I would be seeing a
pop
sorry oh you see came from oh good yeah
where would the power come from I don't
know being we would say like being um
cruel
ignorant uh most animals I mean you can
you can what do you call them you can
fabuliz animals but in general birds fly
away when you come close because all
animals kill each other indiscriminately
constantly their life is a story of
looking over their shoulder and not
getting eaten by another another animal
that's their life so the the essence of
of if I see a paw here it's probably
because I was indiscriminately
disrespectful of all life I ate meat I
killed animals you see and then that put
a seed in my mind and I see a PA where
someone who reached out and helped
people on is seeing an arm same object
try to feel that try to get that feeling
same object is seen in two different
ways by two different people who have
different seeds in their mind okay now
stay with me
okay what is it to be
reborn what has to happen do you have to
get in the shuttle and fly off
somewhere what is it to be born as an
animal what's
required what's required how long does
it take to be reborn as an animal after
you die how long does it take to be
reborn as as an
animal what makes you an
animal it's just a change in your
busness it's a it's a 10c change in your
bustness it takes 10 seconds to go from
human to animal okay that's all you
breathe your last breath 10 seconds
later you're seeing it as a p it's the
same
Li they didn't take you and stuff your
soul into a dog body there's not any
Factory Kansas that's producing dog B
and then people are out with big Nets
catching souls and grabbing them and
shoving them into a dog body try to
understand how dangerous the situation
is what the great danger you and I are
in all the time it takes 10 seconds for
the boset to change you could be an
animal by in in 3 minutes from now you
could be in an animal around it's just
your it's just the karmic sceda shifted
a Tiny Seed the size of the pin of a
needle has shifted in your mind and
you're now it doesn't take a you don't
have to die you know wander around and
look for a body and and go to Kansas and
get a dog body it's not like that that's
all a wrong idea that image of sansar is
wrong there are not five rounds there
isn't like five places somewhere and
there's a map and if you had the right
map you wouldn't have to go there
there's no places there are no
you die your karma sees stop 10 seconds
later you're seeing things in a
different way and that means you were
born as an animal and that's the animal
realm and it's just a perception it's a
shiting perceptions that same shift
occurs when I turn my
hand okay you your seeds in your
mind shift more than it takes to be born
as adult
all right when I turn my hand I'm not
turning my hand your seeds are shifting
your karmas are shifting I'm not turning
my hand okay it's easier to be born as a
dog than to see me turn my
hand okay it requires L change in your
vesselness it's frightening we're in
that situation all the time we're always
on the verge of dying and dying is just
the seeds wore out and then you're on
the verge of being something else and
that's it takes a few seconds and you're
in another realm cuz there is no other
realm it's
just it's a
new thing like that got it it's very
dangerous the life we're living is very
if you don't listen to the G well and
you don't get your ass in gear
then you're in a very dangerous
situation getting liberated is not like
a what do you call it a luxury for
people have the money to come here it's
like if you don't get it going you must
die the the basas that are supporting
your V your vision of this life right
now are very fragile and they go they
move fast especially uh religious ones
you know to be in a in a in a good asham
is expensive karmically extremely
expensive and those karmas are used up
like like that's like burning a cred
card you it's very expensive to be here
karmically to have Swami G be in your
life is is extremely expensive it is the
most the most expensive Karma there is
is to have a sweet authentic
teacher it is the most expensive karma
in the in the universe there is no more
expensive Karma to maintain Swami G or
your heart teacher in your
life if you're not doing really good
stuff all the time they will they will
leave you can't you can't sustain it
it's too expensive it requires too many
good deeds uh to keep them here you see
so anyway I got two
minutes do you I'm going to ask you a
question do you see a bridge now between
the two ideas of what Nirvana
is I'll say them again once School says
if you can stop your negative emotions
you have reached nirvana the other
school says if you reach a place where
you don't have to come back to the
suffering R Sara you have reach nirvana
are they
related you see then there's this great
unification of the two ideas you see the
world is created
bys you the world you see is created by
your negativities you see
you you cannot come back here if you
remove
them yeah yeah he wants to know what's
left okay damn in one minute he wants to
know what's
left what do you think if if if your
caric seats were were completely
pure what where would you
go what would you see
you see I talked about going to the down
I see this um other stick as a as a paw
right what if you go the other
way light what if yeah light it's light
light itself try to grab the light you
know I got light coming down on my bald
head me and Shang uh and uh and you you
can't touch it you see your body will be
made of a substance very similar to that
your body will be made of that no more D
and the cool thing about that body which
is what we said
before is that uh you can multiply it uh
billions of times in every moment of
your existence from then on you can you
can split off bodies to take care of
whole planets billions of planets you
can split off enough bodies to take care
of billions of planets in a second you
can take care I mean the big human need
the the desire of all humanity is to
take care of other people deep down the
biggest desire even more than pizza and
sex is to take care of other people you
want it so bad and you really really
it's so enjoyable it's the highest
pleasure when your body
changes which just means your bom is
Chang change right then uh then you can
take care of billions of planets at the
same time you you could be
the the Shankar Shankar of a whole
planet a billions of planets at the same
time that's
cool that's really cool okay and it's
possible because of this okay so what's
that your your mind is
just rejecting a
paradise okay
nice is it
there theultimate
oh we we say there are physical and
there are mental and there
are Ultimate Reality parts to an
enlightened being enlightened being is
made of three parts one is physical one
is mental and one is the is the ultimate
natur of their being so uh you will be
all free physically you will be a being
of light who can appear on a billion
planets to take care of all of the
people there at the same time physically
mentally you see all past all future
which makes you very good at taking care
of
people and then uh your essence is of
Ultimate
Reality at the same time you are those
three things at the same time cool
that's uh what we call party Nana that's
like super
Nana all right Nana is not the same as
super nana got it so what I I think what
I wanted to do tonight was somehow
reconcile the two versions of Nirvana
one which said that you don't have to
come back here and the other said you're
going to get rid of all your negative
thoughts and then what I want you to get
is that where you come back is created
by your negative s all right it has been
created by
when you turn a page of a
book there's nothing on the
page as your eyes cross the line it
creates the words you see you have
written every book you've ever read as
you read
it like throwing uh Stones down to walk
over you see every book you ever read
every movie you ever saw you created the
next frame from your own conas all right
so you got to see
um Adjustment Bureau you got to see it
[Laughter]
[Applause]
okay
I'd like to thank very much Gish M roach
let's give him a big
hand also to Mercedes for the
singing M roach will continue tomorrow
evening with the program on what is Nana
and tomorrow will be the last uh lecture
in this program and the rest of the
schedule for tomorrow uh main Temple
Puja at 5:00 a.m. here in the temple
5:30 wake up Bell 6:00 a.m. morning
satsang here in the temple tomorrow
morning sat and Nala are going to speak
to us about yogis Without Borders so
SATA are teach